<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter out of Lancashire to a friend in London, giving some account of the late tryals there together with some seasonable and proper remarks upon it, recommended to the wisdom of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament.</title>
            <author>Wagstaffe, Thomas, 1645-1712.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65969</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W208</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8113</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11981438</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11981438</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51853</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65969)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51853)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 522:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter out of Lancashire to a friend in London, giving some account of the late tryals there together with some seasonable and proper remarks upon it, recommended to the wisdom of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament.</title>
                  <author>Wagstaffe, Thomas, 1645-1712.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Thomas Wagstaffe.  Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.)</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lancashire (England) --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51853:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51853:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER OUT OF Lancaſhire TO <hi>A Friend in London,</hi> GIVING Some Account of the Late Tryals there: Together with ſome Seaſonable and Proper Remarks upon it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Recommended to the Wiſdom of the Lords and Commons Aſſembled in Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Among my People are found Wicked Men, they <hi>lay wait,</hi> as he that ſelleth Wares, they ſet a <hi>Trap,</hi> they <hi>Catch</hi> Men,</p>
               <bibl>Jerom. 5.26.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>And <hi>they</hi> watched him, and ſent forth <hi>Spies,</hi> which ſhould <hi>feign</hi> themſelves Juſt Men, that they might take hold of his Words, that ſo they might deliver him unto the Power and Authority of the Governours,</p>
               <bibl>Luk. 20.20.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1694.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:51853:2"/>
            <head>A <hi>LETTER</hi> from <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HOW aſtoniſhing ſoever the Report of the Late <hi>Tryals</hi> in our Country, was with you at <hi>London,</hi> I can aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you the thing it ſelf was no leſs aſtoniſhing here, but muſt more deeply affect us, according as it was more ſenſible to us; and when we ſaw with our eyes, and heard with our ears, the great Scene of Villany, acted by a few Miſcreants, which this or any Age hath known, it ſtruck us with greater Horror and Amazement than any <hi>Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative</hi> could, or can do, how true or full ſoever.</p>
            <p>I do fully agree with you, That ſuch things as theſe do high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſerve the Inquiry and Inſpection of a <hi>Parliament,</hi> both to drive this Myſtery of iniquity to its true <hi>Originals,</hi> to ſearch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſprings which influenced ſuch gratious <hi>Tools and Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and comforted and ſupported them in this Infamous and Helliſh Deſign, and alſo to make ſuch effectual Proviſion for the future, that Innocent Men may hereafter be ſecur'd from having their Lives and Eſtates ſworn away by a Pack of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenary</hi> Villains.</p>
            <p>In Anſwer therefore to yours, and to give them the beſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction I can, I ſhall in the firſt place give you a ſhort Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Material Evidences on both ſides; and then in the next place, make ſome proper Reflexions in order to diſcover the Principals, or who ſet theſe Monſters on work, were the Fomentors and Abettors of the Deſign, and more guilty than the vile Inſtruments themſelves.</p>
            <p>But before I enter upon this, I muſt Acquaint you of one ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Defect, that what I am going to ſay unavoidably la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours under; I mean there is ſomething I would, but cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, and that is the <hi>Tranſcendent and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nparallell'd Impudence</hi> of <hi>Lunt</hi> and his Partners; I can tell you their Words, and the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:51853:2"/>parts of their Evidence, but the <hi>Form,</hi> the Audacious Bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with which they delivered themſelves, the <hi>Brow of Braſs</hi> far ſurmounts all the Language I was ever Maſter of, this there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you muſt ſupply, and conceive as well as you can; and if you have any Conception of Atheiſm and Blaſphemy, if a ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Conſcience of the Air of Hell, and Obdurateneſs of Devils, from all together perhaps you may frame ſome Idaea of it. And this you are to conceive to be as the <hi>Soul</hi> to the <hi>Body</hi> of their Evidence, the whole in the whole, and the whole in every part of it. And if to all and every Word of it, you joyn the higheſt <hi>Impudence</hi> to the <hi>Perjury,</hi> it is the leaſt Calculation I am able to give you.</p>
            <p>Thus (after the Formalities of the Court were over, as read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Commiſſion, Calling over the Jury, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) on <hi>Thurſday</hi> Morning Sir <hi>Giles Eyes</hi> gave the Charge; I ſhall not give you the whole Speech, as not <hi>neceſſary,</hi> or if it were ſo, not <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le;</hi> for though it was taken in ſhort-hand, yet Sir <hi>Giles</hi> took care to prevent the ſpreading, by tearing the Books of all thoſe he obſerv'd to write, yet what concern'd the immediate Matter, was, that after an extolling the Juſtice of the Court, the Folly of diſturbing it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he told them, That <hi>twas the Treachery of their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful Countrymen which brought the trouble of a ſpecial Commiſſion upon them, that ſome of the Conſpirators were Proteſtants of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>as they called themſelves; and though Popery and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtancy was like the Image of</hi> Nebuchadnezzar, <hi>whoſe ſect was Clay and Iron, which would not mix well together, yet that here they did both agree to diſturb the Peace, but there might be at leaſt a lengthening our tranquility, and that others (deterred by their Pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhment) might hear, and fear, and do no more ſo wickedly, it was put into the hands of the Jury, to Hear, and to Accuſe for theſe Crimes which would be ſworn before them:</hi> And Concluded, <hi>that he hoped they would ſo behave themſelves, that they ſhould not need any C<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mmendations from him, but that their own Works ſhould praiſe them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Afternoon the Grand Jury found Four Bills of Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>One</hi> againſt Sir <hi>Rowland Stanley,</hi> Sir <hi>Tho. Clifton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Dic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Langton,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Blundel,</hi> and the other Three a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord <hi>Molineaux,</hi> Sir <hi>William Gerard,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Walmſly,</hi> ſeverally, upon Oath they were all Arraign'd, Sir <hi>Will. Gerard</hi> with great importunity begg'd Time till <hi>Saturday</hi> for his Tryal,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51853:3"/>but was denyed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Ordered to prepare for his Tryal the next Morning by Nine: A Propoſal was then made to the ſaid Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Whether they would be Tryed ſeverally, or joyntly, and one of them Challenge for all, and they deſired Time till next Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to give their Anſwers, and a Copy of the Pannel, which was granted, and a Copy delivered them, which contained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout an Hundred Names. The next Morning being brought into Court, they agreed to the Propoſal, provided the Kings Councel would ſhew the Cauſe of their Challenges at the ſame time they made them, otherwiſe they would each of them inſiſt on their Challenges; but that was denyed, and the Court told them, that unleſs they would without any Conditions ſubmit to the Propoſal, one of their Tryals ſhould immediately begin. This forced them to give their Conſent, and then the Court told them they ſhould be Tryed next Morning, and Ordered them to be taken away. And immediately after they were gone, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Motion of Mr. <hi>Aaron Smith,</hi> the Court Ordered near a Hundred more to be returned upon the Jury, and threatned the Sheriffe if he did not do it, and it was done accordingly.</p>
            <p>An Order was alſo given to the Clerk of the Crown, That no <hi>Sub Paena's</hi> ſhould be made for any of the Priſoners, until the Names of the Witneſſes were firſt brought to ſome of the Judges, or to Mr. <hi>Aaron Smith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On <hi>Saturday</hi> Morning the Priſoners were brought to the Bar, and the ſaid Gentlemen put upon their Tryal; 120 of the Jury appeared, and the Kings Council Challenged every Perſon who was either a <hi>Member of Parliament, Deputy Lieutenant, or Juſtice ſo the Peace.</hi> The Names of ſome of them are, Sir <hi>Edw. Chiſenhall,</hi> Mr. <hi>Farrington,</hi> Mr. <hi>Maudeſley,</hi> Mr. <hi>Blackhorn,</hi> Mr. <hi>Molineax,</hi> and in all to the Number of Thirty Eight Men of great Note and Conſideration in their Country, and (which makes it more ſtrange) have been active and rigorous for the Intereſt of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in their reſpective Stations, and more particularly as Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners for the raiſing of Money. The Gentlemen only Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged Twenty Four.</p>
            <p>After the Jury was fixt and Sworn, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Witneſſes gave their Evidence: The firſt for the King was <hi>Lunt,</hi> the Subſtance of whoſe Evidence was this, That in <hi>June</hi> or <hi>July</hi> (which he is not certain) 1689. he delivered ſeveral Commiſſions from King <hi>James</hi> to the ſaid <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> met together at a Grand
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51853:3"/>Conſult at my Lord <hi>Molineux</hi>'s Houſe at <hi>Croxton;</hi> upon which being ask'd, whether he knew that theſe Priſoners at the Bar, were the Perſons to whom he delivered the Commiſſions: He ſwore that he knew them all very <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly</hi> and well, and that theſe were the very Perſons. Sir <hi>W. W.</hi> for more ſatisfaction to the Court and Jury, bid him point out Sir <hi>R. Stanley, Lunt</hi> pointed to Sir <hi>Tho. Clifton,</hi> and ſaid that was Sir <hi>R. Stanley;</hi> upon which there was a great <hi>Hum</hi> among the Spectators. But to rectifie this, he was ordered to take the Cryers ſtaff and lay it upon the Head of Sir <hi>R. Stanley;</hi> he took the ſtaff, and (though prompted by his Fellows; and had what intimation was poſſible from the Judge) yet he layd it on the Head of Sir <hi>T. Clifton,</hi> and with unparallell'd impudence, ſaid he was Sir <hi>R. Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley.</hi> However Sir <hi>George Eyres</hi> excuſed this, and ſaid, <hi>There was no great matterin that miſtake, for that thoſe Gentlemen were together at</hi> Croxton, <hi>and were together at the Bar, and the miſtake of one for another, was no great matter:</hi> So on he went, and ſwore he delivered Commiſſions to thoſe Gentlemen, to be Collonels, Captains, Lieutenants reſpectively, that they receiv'd theſe Commiſſions with joy, and kiſs'd them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and each gave him 5 <hi>l.</hi> that they advis'd with him what Method to take to Raiſe the Men, and at laſt concluded to ſend him to <hi>London,</hi> to Liſt what <hi>Iriſh</hi> and others he could; and accordingly he went and Liſted 60. and bought Arms to the Value of 50 <hi>l.</hi> being ſupplyed with Money by Mr. <hi>Whitplace,</hi> by Order of the Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and who had direction from them to let him have what Money he had occaſion for; that upon his return theſe Gentlemen thanked him, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ſent him to St. <hi>Germains</hi> to acquaint K. <hi>James</hi> and the Lord <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> with the forwardneſs of Affairs in <hi>England;</hi> that K. <hi>J.</hi> diſpatch'd him back again to acquaint his Friends how ſoon he would be with them; that upon his return to the Gentlemen, each made Anſwer that they wiſhed for that hour, ſeeing all of them had compleated their deſigns.</p>
            <p>The next Witneſs was <hi>Womble,</hi> who (being a Carryer) ſwore that at ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times he carryed down <hi>Arms</hi> to theſe Gentlemen, that he came to know them to be <hi>Arms,</hi> for that a Black Mare of his going to drink, fell into the Water, ſo that he ventured to open the Box to ſee what damage the Goods had, and perceived them to be <hi>Arms;</hi> that being found a <hi>Truſty Man</hi> he was often imployed afterwards on the ſame occaſion, that ſome of the Boxes were directed to Mr. <hi>Dickenſon,</hi> others to others, and that he ſaw them take their Proportions upon the Delivery:</p>
            <p>The next was <hi>Wilſon,</hi> who ſwore that he was imploy'd to wait for the Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Lunt,</hi> and to conduct him where thoſe Gentlemen were, who finding them at <hi>Croxton,</hi> ſaw Mr. <hi>Lunt</hi> deliver the Commiſſions to them, which they joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully receiv'd. That he ſaw ſeveral of the Men liſted by <hi>Lunt,</hi> who quartered up and down, and that he was very well acquainted with thoſe two, who were at Sir <hi>R. Stanley</hi>'s; and in ſhort, in all things he corroborates <hi>Lunt's</hi> Teſtimony.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51853:4"/>The next was <hi>Breuerlon,</hi> who ſwore, that having in <hi>Ireland</hi> ſerv'd K. <hi>James,</hi> he having no further Service for him, he came, for <hi>England,</hi> and being well entertained by thoſe Gentlemen, received at their hands a Commiſſion from K. <hi>James;</hi> That whilſt K. <hi>James</hi> was at <hi>La Hague,</hi> he was at <hi>Worrell,</hi> and Sir <hi>R. Stanley</hi> uſed to give him Money, as ſeveral Sums at 3 times, 10 <hi>s.</hi> 5 <hi>s.</hi> 15 <hi>s.</hi> which he looked upon to be given him, that he might be ready when K. <hi>James</hi> Landed. And this the Judge (out of pure Charity to the Priſoners no doubt) called <hi>Subſiſtance Money.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Evidence, for the Priſoners, though not in the ſame Order (which is needleſs) but in Subſtance, is as follows:</p>
            <p>One <hi>Parſons</hi> teſtified that <hi>Lunt</hi> promiſed him 150 <hi>l.</hi> if he would Swear to what he would have him.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Leigh Banchs</hi> teſtified, that he was introduc'd into <hi>Lunt</hi>'s company by Mr. <hi>Taffe,</hi> that <hi>Lunt</hi> ſeemed well pleaſed at it, and would needs have him oblig'd to Secrecy. That <hi>Lunt</hi> told him, he might if he would have been in <hi>Dodſworth</hi>'s Plot; that he had two, <hi>Womble</hi> and <hi>Wilſon</hi> to back his Evidence, but becauſe they were ignorant Fellows, he would turn them off, if he could but get 2 or 3 Gentlemen (like, himſelf) who would better manage his Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, and bring his Plot to a better Concluſion. He ask'd him, if he could write well, if he could, he ſhould be imployed in writing Commiſſions; for he could get an Old Commiſſion of K. <hi>James</hi>'s, and a Paſs from my Lord <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,</hi> and they might eaſily counterfeit their Hands. He promiſed him great Rewards, and put him in hopes of the Gentlemens Eſtates. And that if <hi>this took,</hi> he would go all over <hi>England,</hi> and Impeach diſtinct men in their ſeveral Countries.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Taffe</hi> (who brought Mr. <hi>Ba<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ks</hi> acquainted with <hi>Lunt,</hi> and was privy to <hi>Lunt</hi>'s Deſigns) confirm'd in all points Mr. <hi>Banks</hi>'s Evidence, and added that <hi>Lunt</hi> complain'd of the blockiſhneſs of <hi>Womble</hi> and <hi>Wilſon,</hi> and ſwore they knew no more than what he had prompted them to; and that <hi>Lunt</hi> gave as a Reaſon why he went to ſeize Mr. <hi>Leigh</hi> of <hi>Lime, that he might know him, and his Houſe, when he came to the Tryal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Dickenſon</hi> going to give his Evidence, paſſed by <hi>Lunt,</hi> and ſaid to him, Doſt thou know me? To which <hi>Lunt</hi> reply'd, <hi>God d</hi>— <hi>thee, I thought thou hadſt been an honeſter Man than to have betray'd me.</hi> He teſtify'd that by Mr. <hi>Taffe</hi>'s means, getting into <hi>Lunt</hi>'s company, <hi>Lunt</hi> asked him his Name; who replyed <hi>Howard,</hi> An honourable Name, ſaid <hi>Lunt,</hi> it will be for the Merit of the Cauſe. Then he asked him, What is your Religion? Of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſaid <hi>D.</hi> That's well, ſaid <hi>Lunt,</hi> then you muſt ſwear you received a Commiſſion from Mr. <hi>Leigh of Lime,</hi> becauſe he is a <hi>Proteſtant.</hi> Then he asked, whether he knew theſe Gentlemen? Yes, (ſaid he) very well. That's well ſaid <hi>Lunt:</hi> I my ſelf have delivered a Commiſſion with my own Hands to one <hi>Roger Dickenſon</hi> (being the Perſon to whom he ſpoke, under the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guized
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51853:4"/>Name of <hi>Howard</hi>) do you know him likewiſe? Yes (ſaith Mr. <hi>D.</hi>) I know him extraordinary well. Then, ſaith <hi>Lunt,</hi> things will go on finely.</p>
            <p>What Reſpected the general Credit of the <hi>King's Witneſſes,</hi> it was proved by many <hi>Credible and unexceptionable</hi> Witneſſes; That <hi>Lunt</hi> was a <hi>Bigamiſt and a Highway-man.</hi> To which the Judge ſaid, That ſignified little, becauſe theſe Perſons knowing it did not proſecute him. That <hi>Womble</hi> ſwore he would have the Blood of <hi>Papiſts;</hi> and he got 100 <hi>l. per Annum</hi> by Swearing; That he ſtole Money at <hi>Croſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y,</hi> when he went there to ſearch, which Money dropt out of his Boots when the Meſſenger cauſed him to be ſearcht. That <hi>VVilſon</hi> was a <hi>Thief,</hi> and ſtole 4 Cows; and the Record was produc'd in Court of his being <hi>burnt in the Hand.</hi> That <hi>Breuerton</hi> had often ſwore that Sir <hi>R. Stanley</hi> was a <hi>ſne<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>king Fellow,</hi> becauſe he would give him no Money, but he would be even with him one time or other.</p>
            <p>What reſpected the Time and Circumſtances of the Fact charged upon thoſe Gentlemen, it was proved beyond Contradiction.</p>
            <p>That Sir <hi>R. Stanley</hi> was at his own Houſe in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> and not in <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> all that Year that <hi>Lunt</hi> ſwore that he was at <hi>Croxton</hi> that in particular, for the months of <hi>June</hi> and <hi>July</hi> he was ſeen in Bed Morning and Evening, proved by his Lady's Woman, and his <hi>Valet de Chambre.</hi> That the reſt of the Priſoners were actually, in Cuſtody in <hi>Mancheſter</hi> at the ſame time, and many months af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that <hi>Lunt</hi> ſwore they were at <hi>Croxton.</hi> That Mr. <hi>VValmſly</hi> was at that time and two Years before and after in <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Particulars I give you in ſhort, but they were plainly prov'd, and ſufficiently convinc'd the Jury, and indeed all who heard the Tryal.</p>
            <p>From all together you may pleaſe to obſerve what Infinite Care was taken to deſtroy theſe Innocent Gentlemen, and to Ruine their Families forever. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Here was as Fine and plauſible Contrivance as could be fram'd, and one part made to hang to another ſo artificially, as might make it ſeem probable to, and take with the Jury. <hi>Lunt</hi> he delivers Commiſſions from K. <hi>James; VVilſon</hi> was by and ſaw the delivery, and knew ſome of the men raiſed by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of them; <hi>Breuerton</hi> received a Commiſſion from them, and <hi>VVomble</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd the <hi>Arms</hi> in purſuance of the Deſign. This it muſt be confeſſed was compleatly laid, and was ſufficient to Hang a whole Country.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Judge in his Charge indeavouring to prepoſſeſs the Jury, and to perſwade them, and to inſinuate to them, as if the Fact charged upon the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, had been Notorious and Self-Evident, as is plainly the deſign of his Speech, and the meaning of his Words.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The adding near a 100 men to the Jury, after the Priſoners had a Copy of it, and after the Court had made a particular agreement with them, to take their Tryals joyntly, and not ſeverally.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The King's Council challenging all the <hi>Members of Parliament, Juſtices, Deputy-Lieutenants,</hi> and leaving none of the Jury, but men of inferiour Rank,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51853:5"/>and there was not one <hi>Gentleman</hi> of the Jury, or one who poll'd as ſuch, which is a plain caſe that theſe men were thought too noble to be entruſted with an Affair of this Nature, And if to this I may add,</p>
            <p n="5">5. That after all Mr. <hi>A. Smith</hi> ſaid. That <hi>if he had been of the Jury, he would certainly have brought them in guilty every man of them.</hi> And I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he may be believ'd without ſwearing.</p>
            <p>And yet notwithſtanding Providence ſo ordered the Matter, that the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemens Lives were not only ſav'd, but that it hath alſo faſtened an indeleble ſteyne of Infamy on the Witneſſes, and all their Abettors.</p>
            <p>Sir, here you have in ſhort, the Portraicture of this black Villany; ſo far, I mean, as appears bare face'd: But you conceive (and I think rightly) that there is a great deal more behind the Curtain, ſome ſecret and inviſible ſprings which moved the Machine, ſome who contriv'd the Buſineſs, prom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted theſe ungodly Inſtruments, and taught them their Leſſon, and abetted them in the Proſecution and Management: And this brings me to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thing you ſeem to require my Sentiments of, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What may be offer'd in order to the diſcovery of the <hi>Principals,</hi> who ſet them on work, and were privy to the Secret, and acceſſary to the Guilt: And this you think worthy of the Wiſdom of a <hi>Parliament,</hi> and certainly it is ſo, if any thing be ſo; for ſuch Practices deſtroy not only all our <hi>Liberties,</hi> but our <hi>Lives</hi> alſo at once: And if ſuch Rogues ſhall be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanc'd, penſion'd, and taught to ſwear againſt innocent Men, our <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Priviledges</hi> are not our ſafety, but ruine; give me an Hundred Arbitrary Kings, rather than to lye at the Mercy of an Arbitrary Raſcal, who will ſwear himſelf to the Devil, and any Man out of his Life for a Suit of Fine Cloathes, and Money to ſpend at a Tavern; and our Liberties are fine things indeed, when they are under the Power of ſuch Men who have Conſcience enough to ſwear any thing, and Wit enough to learn the Leſſon that is taught them.</p>
            <p>And therefore in Anſwer to this Particular, I ſhall enquire into theſe Two Things.
<list>
                  <item>1. Whether it be any means probable that theſe Men were the Contrivers of this wicked Deſign; and if not, then,</item>
                  <item>2. What Marks and Characters may be layd down to aſſiſt us in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Matter, and where theſe are found, it is highly probable, that thoſe are in the bottom, or at leaſt, it is worthy the beſt inquiry of the Parliament whether they be or no.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>In order to the Firſt Inquiry, I ſhall conſider the Character of the Perſons, and the Nature of the thing.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Character of the Perſons, they were theſe Four, <hi>Lunt, Womble, Wilſon, Breuerton; Lunt</hi> (the Principal, and on whom the reſt depended) was a <hi>Coach-man, Womble</hi> a <hi>Carryer, Wilſon</hi> a <hi>Tapſter, Breuerton</hi> a <hi>Sadlers
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51853:5"/>Prentice,</hi> and who ran from his Maſter. And are not theſe Men rarely qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified to make a <hi>Plot,</hi> and ſet it ſo artificially together? If it be ſaid the ſubject of their Evidence was Matter of Fact, and ſo not above their Capacities. Right, and this ſhews the Cunning of the Contrivance; for it would have been extreamly ridiculous to have brought theſe men to have given Evidence concerning Myſteries of State, and Councils of Princes: But a <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> and <hi>Arms,</hi> and ſuch things were within their Sphere; and a Carrier may be qualified enough to know a Piſtol from a Sword; and a Box of Arms (if the Box be open) from a Box of Sagar Plumbs. But this is not the Caſe: Their Capacities are not queſtion'd, for knowing one thing, or one man from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, (although <hi>Lum</hi> was a little miſtaken in that matter) but for the whole Contrivance, and I hope there are more Brains and Politicks that go to the making of a Plot, than to the meer ſwearing to it, which only requires a hard Forehead, and a little Memory, and no Conſcince: The Web was artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially weav'd, and the Deſign laid well enough, and had certainly carry'd their Point, and Hang'd the Gentlemen, had it not been for the Folly of the Inſtruments, which is one argument more for their incapacity for the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance: For <hi>Lunt</hi> is a <hi>Fool</hi> as well as a <hi>Coach-man,</hi> and his being ſo eaſily ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and div'd into, his opening the whole matter to Mr. <hi>Barks</hi> and Mr. <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenſon,</hi> whom he had never ſeen before; as it was the Providential means to diſcover the Villany, ſo it apparently ſhewed the Contrivance could be none of his. The Inquiry therefore turns upon this Point, here is a plain and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted <hi>Contrivance</hi> apparent to all Men, and granted by the Court it ſelf, very artiſicially and cloſely put together, the Evidence exactly ſet according to the Form of Law, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if any man in his Wits can think that ſuch Men as theſe were the Principal Authors, he may with as much reaſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that <hi>Coachmen</hi> and <hi>Tapſters</hi> are qualified to make <hi>Secretaries of State, Lord-Keepers,</hi> and <hi>Archbiſhops.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Another thing to be conſidered, is the <hi>Nature of the Thing.</hi> And here (I think) it will not be inquired, whether any Man will <hi>Forſwear</hi> himſelf, meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the ſake of <hi>Forſwearing,</hi> and the great delight and ſatisfaction he takes in <hi>Perjury,</hi> or murder Men by <hi>falſe Oaths,</hi> becauſe he loves to ſee them Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the Gallows, how wicked ſo ever men are, This is incompatible with humane Nature, and a ſtrain beyond the Devils themſelves. And therefore I may take it for granted, that <hi>Lunt</hi> and his Fellows did not <hi>conſpire</hi> to give their Souls to the Devil <hi>gratis,</hi> or indeavour to <hi>ſwear</hi> half the Gentlemen of a Country out of their Lives, meerly for the pleaſure of ſeeing them <hi>hang'd.</hi> And therefore whoſoever will reſolve to think that Theſe are the Principal, or the Only Conſpirators, in compliance to the common Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of Mankind, is bound to aſſign ſome Cauſe that might provoke them to ſo Flagitious a Villany. And I believe the Wit of Man can find but two, either <hi>Revenge,</hi> or <hi>Reward.</hi> As for <hi>Revenge,</hi> it is a terrible Paſſion indeed, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51853:6"/>prompts men, under the power of it, to do any thing; but then it hath its proper object, and is never exercis'd upon men who never injur'd, nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oblig'd us. And what Injury or Diſobligation had the 4 Conſpirators receiv'd from theſe Gentlemen? why truly no more but this, that <hi>Breuerton</hi> had ſaid that one of them <hi>was aſneaking Fellow, and would give him no Money;</hi> which is but a poor Reaſon for ſuch a terrible Revenge: And yet he ſwears that he gave him 30 <hi>s.</hi> at ſeveral times. But let that paſs, what is that to the Reſt of the Gentlemen? did they ever refuſe him any Money? or did he ever expect any from them? and yet he Swore againſt all the Gentlemen, as well as againſt that <hi>One.</hi> And what is this to the other 3 Conſpirators? was ever <hi>Lunt,</hi> or <hi>VVomble,</hi> or <hi>Wilſon,</hi> diſoblig'd by them? why truly not at all, and it plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appears that <hi>Lunt</hi> (the Principal of <hi>them</hi>) was ſo far from being diſob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd by them, that he had never ſeen ſome of them (perhaps any of them) all his Life. So that whatever elſe may be aſſigned as the occaſion of this <hi>Bloody Conſpiracy,</hi> Revenge could be none of it. And then as for <hi>Reward,</hi> This in truth is a Reaſon probable enough, and in all likelihood the only Reaſon: But then I doubt this will extend farther, and involve others in the Guilt. Who Rewarded them? who promis'd and encourag, d them? Theſe are material Queſtions, and more fit to be ſpoke to in the next Head, which is,</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Laying down ſome Marks, to direct us to the Diſcovery of the other Conſpirators and Abetters in this Helliſh Deſign.</p>
            <p>And the Firſt Inquiry may be this, Who maintained theſe <hi>mean Fellows</hi> at that <hi>Splended Rate? Lunt</hi> the Coachman was habited like a General, nothing finer or richer, with his <hi>Footman</hi> to attend him, and his other Expences were proportionable, and he lived at the rate of a Thouſand pound a Year. <hi>Wilſon</hi> the Tapſter kept his Gelding, and took his Pleaſure like a Man of Rank and Eſtate. <hi>Womble</hi> ſaid he had a 100 <hi>l. per Annum</hi> for Swearing. And the other was maintained with equal Proportions: And what was all this for, think you? Money is not ſo plentiful at this time of Day, to be ſquandred away for nothing. And a man may honeſtly ſuppoſe that ſuch profuſe Lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes were not exhibited to them out of pure Love to their Perſons; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was to be done by them that might anſwer the Charges? and wherein the <hi>Paymaſters</hi> might find their Account. And ſurely when men Swear ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly and truly, there is no ſuch need of <hi>Greaſing</hi> and <hi>Daubing:</hi> But it muſt be confeſs'd a <hi>falſe Oath</hi> wants pampering, and high feeding: and when men are provoked to Forſwear themſelves, they need ſupply from time to time to keep up their Spirits againſt the Reluctancy of their Conſciences. This is a dreadful Caſe in a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Nation, and deſerves the utmoſt Care of the Parliament upon a Double Account.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. To Examine throughly what becomes of the Money they have given, and to what Uſes applyed, leaſt it be diverted to harbour and cheriſh Proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate Rogues to cut their own Throats.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:51853:6"/> 
               <hi>2dly.</hi> It is the moſt infamous and ſhameleſs Practice, and unſufferable among civiliz'd People, that <hi>Beggars</hi> and <hi>Villains</hi> ſhould be maintain'd like <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> for no other reaſon or purpoſe, but to Swear away the Lives of other Men. Whoever Bribes his Witneſſes, demonſtrates the Injuſtice of his Cauſe, and renders their Teſtimony ſuſpected; and what can be ſaid of this Scandalous Practice to keep a <hi>Fund</hi> for <hi>Perjury</hi> and <hi>Murder.</hi> It is high time for the Parliament to look about them, when theſe Courſes grow every day upon us; the Caſes of <hi>Fuller, Young</hi> and <hi>Blacket</hi> were enough to open our Eyes, but when the ſame things are multiplyed upon us, and the ſame Game played over again by a New-Set of Inſtruments, we muſt be more then ſtupid, if we do not ſee the deſign againſt our Lives and Fortunes. And in truth things are now come to that paſs, that there is ſcarcely a Rogue in the three Kingdoms, but when he finds Hunger and Want pinches him, but hath his Reſolution ready; why forſooth, he will not ſtarve, and then he goes to ſet up the Trade of Swearing, to ſupply his VVants, and maintain his Vices. And this, it ſeems, is a ſure and eaſie way, and there is a Stock ready for all Comers; it looks as if there were a <hi>Bank,</hi> for Swearing, to promote the Trade, for it is all their Cry, <hi>We ſhall have Money enough;</hi> But ſurely it becomes the <hi>Wiſdom of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to ſee from whence, and by whom all theſe great Sums are ſupply'd; for this is not only to Licence Perjury, but to purchaſe it; and it is a certain rule both in Divinity and Law, that he that bribes and ſupports a falſe Oath, is not only conſenting to it, but more guilty than him that ſwears it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We muſt yet further conſider the Character of the Perſons, but in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Capacity, not as to their deſpicableneſs and meanneſs, but with reſpect to their Morality, and Infamy; <hi>Wilſon</hi> was a common Thief, and Burnt in the Hand in that very Country where he gave his Evidence; and <hi>Lunt</hi> a High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way-man, and hath two Wives. Sufficient to deſtroy their Credit with all wiſe and juſt men: and whoever makes uſe of their Evidence, will, by all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different men, be ſuppos'd to have the ſame deſign with them. Now although a Man may be a very great Villain, yet if at the ſame time his Crimes are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, another man may credit him himſelf, and proceed upon his Teſtimony, and yet be very innocent; but this I doubt, can never be ſaid of a Perſon, who ſufficiently <hi>knows</hi> his Villany, and yet makes uſe of him, to the deſtruction of others. And this is apparently the Caſe, <hi>Lum</hi>'s wickedneſs was open and notorious, he was indicted upon the Statute for having two VVives, and the Bill was found, and Mr. <hi>Aarom Smith,</hi> one of the Proſecutors, becomes his <hi>Bail,</hi> though the Caſe was <hi>Felony,</hi> and not only ſo, but when <hi>Lunt</hi> came to be tryed, he and his Bail both forfeited their Renogniſances, which is a demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strative proof, not only that <hi>Lum</hi>'s Infamy was known to the Proſecutors, but that for his ſake they eluded the Law, and skreen'd him from the ſentence of it. And this I think, will deſerve the Inquiry of a Parliament, upon more accounts than one; for 'tis certainly a terrible Caſe, unheard of by <hi>Engliſh
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51853:7"/>men,</hi> not only that <hi>Criminals,</hi> under the immediate proſecution of the Law, ſhould be made Evidences againſt mens Lives, but that the Courſe of Juſtice ſhould be obſtructed in favour of a job of <hi>Perjury,</hi> they were to undertake.</p>
            <p>To which may be added,</p>
            <p n="3">3. The mighty hunt that was made about the Town by Officers and Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, after Men who ſaid anything tending to the reproach of the <hi>King's Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi> together with <hi>Warrants</hi> of a ſtrange and illegal nature, to ſeize, &amp; take up Men &amp; their Papers <hi>for Conſpiring and indeavouring to ſuborn</hi> (as the Warrants word it) Witneſſes againſt the Lives and Credit of ſeveral Witneſſes for their Majeſties, againſt Perſons charg'd with High Treaſon; Upon which ſome very worthy and conſiderable Men were taken up, and kept cloſe priſoners for ſome time, and are yet under Bail, contrary to all Law and Juſtice: But the plain deſign of this was, not to terrifie men from ſpeaking what all the Town knew, but, by taking up as many as they could meet with, to prevent any Perſons going to tell the Truth at the Tryal, and confront their Evidence. And any man, who conſiders theſe Methods, can never doubt, but that, if they had but known the <hi>Gentlemen's Witneſſes,</hi> they would have taken care to have ſtopt their Mouths, and by ſuch <hi>Arbitrary</hi> VVarrants, have cooped them up cloſe Priſoners, from whence they ſhould never have been freed, till the <hi>Gentlemen</hi> had been <hi>hang'd.</hi> And it is very obſervable that theſe <hi>Warrants,</hi> and <hi>Spies,</hi> were ſent abroad in every Corner, but a little before the <hi>Gentlemen</hi> were car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd down to their Tryal. But Providence ſo ordered it, that thoſe, whom they Principally aimed at, eſcaped their Fingers, and the <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all their foul indeavours to the contrary, had honeſt men enough to detect the Falſhood of the pack'd Evidence, and to ſave their Lives. Now put theſe two together, the Direct and Actual obſtruction of Juſtice in the caſe of <hi>Lunt,</hi> and the great indeavours to do ſo in the Caſe of theſe Gentlemen, by impriſoning their VVitneſſes, and that too by illegal and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary methods, and I will leave it with any man, whether thoſe Perſons, by whoſe Influence all this was done, can be excuſed from being <hi>Encouragers</hi> and <hi>Abettors</hi> of this Bloody Deſign, if not the Principal Contrivers and Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of it. He that <hi>ſtreyns</hi> the Law in point of Life, is a down-right <hi>Murderer,</hi> and here we have no leſs than a threefold violation of the Law, and all to take away the Lives of Innocent Men: and let thoſe Perſons, who have been concerned in ſuch Practices, diſcharge themſelves from the Imputation, if they can.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Groat <hi>Promiſes</hi> that were made in this particular, deſerve Inquiry, Mr. <hi>Parſon's</hi> teſtifies that <hi>Lunt</hi> promis'd him 150 <hi>l.</hi> to Swear, and Mr. <hi>Banks</hi> that he promis'd him <hi>great Rewards, putting him in hopes of the Gentlemens Eſtates,</hi> Now upon this, this Queſtion ariſes, VVho could make good theſe Promiſes? who could give ſuch <hi>great Rewards?</hi> In ſhort, who could give the <hi>Gentlemens Eſtates</hi> to theſe Varlets, had they been convicted by their Perjury?
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51853:7"/>But it is more ſit for me to leave theſe Queſtions to the Inquiry of a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, only I ſhall leave theſe Remarks to their ſerious Conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That whoſoever <hi>Rewards</hi> Perjury and Murder, is guilty of them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That thoſe Perſons, who promiſed theſe Gentlemens, Eſtates to theſe Miſcreants, muſt be ſatisfied themſelves of the Perjury, becauſe the Reward was otherwiſe ſo vaſtly diſproportionate to the undertaking.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That if ſuch Temptations ſhall be laid in the way of <hi>Rogues</hi> to <hi>promiſe Gentlemens Eſtates</hi> to thoſe who will Swear them out of their Lives: If the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> do not take care to obviate it, there is never a <hi>Lord</hi> nor <hi>Commoner</hi> can be ſafe, ſo long as there is an <hi>Eſtate,</hi> and a <hi>Rogue</hi> in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. It deſerves to be considered, That the Warrants for the Execution of theſe Gentlemen were Sign'd, and there were Directions given, that they ſhould be Executed 3 Days after their Condemnation. From whence theſe, things are obvious. <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the Projectors thought themſelves ſure of their Buſineſs, and well they might, when they had taken ſo much care to inſtruct the Evidence, and to prevent the diſcovery of their Infamy. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> That the Deſign was plainly laid for <hi>Blood,</hi> and which they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to have, whatever came on it. And therefore the <hi>Gentlemen</hi> were to be, diſpatched, before any Applications could be made either for Pardon, or for reſpiting the Sentence: and before the Inconſiſtency, Contradiction and Falſhood of <hi>their</hi> Witneſſes Teſtimony could be known, which even after Sentence, in juſtice, ought to have preſerv'd them from it. But it ſeems the <hi>Wiſe Contrivers</hi> thought it was good to be ſure, and to prevent all after-claps, they were forthwith to be <hi>Hang'd out of the way;</hi> which is a manifeſt evidence of a Deep and wide Conſederacy to take away their Lives. For <hi>Thirdly,</hi> it is impoſſible that any thing of this, (of ſigning the Warrants for Execution, and Orders to do it ſo haſtily) could be aſcrib'd to <hi>Luct,</hi> and his Accomplices, and conſequently muſt have ſome other <hi>Authors,</hi> and who theſe are will be very caſie for the Eye of the Parliament to diſcern. To this may be added:</p>
            <p n="6">6. That at the ſame time, there were <hi>bla<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k Warrants</hi> ſent down to take up <hi>two hundred</hi> Gentlemen more in the Counties of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> and <hi>Cheſter,</hi> in order to proſecute them for their Lives by the ſame Methods. And this was to have been put in Execution ſo soon as the other Gentlemen had been diſpatch'd, which makes the <hi>Deſign</hi> as plain, as the Noſe in a Man's Face, and directly points to the Managers and Contrivers: And ſarely it ſeems to me as if there was a deſign to root out all the Gentry of <hi>England,</hi> at leaſt ſo many of them, who did not ſtand fair with the Contrivers, or would not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with whatſoever they ſhould propoſe to them. As <hi>Lunt</hi> vaunted, that <hi>ſo soon as he had made an end of this buſineſs, he would go all over</hi> England <hi>on the ſame Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand.</hi> And this is the plain ſtate of the Caſe, a <hi>Plot</hi> was to be had at any Rate, and becauſe they could not find one, they made one themſelves, and theſe Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen were to be <hi>hang'd</hi> in Confirmation of it, and then they thought they had
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51853:8"/>the Kingdom in a ſtring; and whoſoever ſhould obſtruct their <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Courſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, or not agree to all their Demands, how unreaſonable ſoever, it was but ſwearing them into the <hi>Plot,</hi> and there was an end of them. The <hi>Tymeing</hi> of this highly deſerves Conſideration, it was juſt before the preſent Seſſion of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> and in all probability, the <hi>Money Bill</hi> will not paſs ſo eaſily, at leaſt in ſuch proportions, as ſome Men may require, ſuch prodigious Sums having been given already, and the Kingdom exhauſted to the very Bones; but here was a Method to ram it down their Throats, the <hi>Deſtroying Evidences</hi> hang over their heads, and there was no <hi>Medium,</hi> either <hi>Give</hi> or be <hi>Hang'd.</hi> And are we not in a comfortable Condition, and have great reaſon to Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in our Freedom, when a few <hi>Perjur'd Villains</hi> were ſet up and maintain'd to over-awe the Parliament, and to bring the Gentry to their Bow, or elſe to depopulate the Nation. It is a ſine Device, to hang up ſome to terrifie others, to ſet up the <hi>Devil</hi> of <hi>Evidences,</hi> to ſcare People out of their <hi>Liberties:</hi> If this be not <hi>Slavery</hi> with a Vengeance, no man living knows what it is.</p>
            <p>Theſe are Conſiderations antecedent to the Tryal, but there are ſome which are ſubſequent to it, and deſerve to be conſider'd, for the further unmasking this <hi>Bloody Villany:</hi> They are theſe Two for the preſent, and no doubt but Time will diſcover more.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It deſerves to be Conſidered, who they are, that are extreamly <hi>diſpleas'd</hi> and <hi>diſſatisfied</hi> that the Tryal did not take effect, who are very <hi>angry</hi> and <hi>peeviſh</hi> that the Gentlemen are not hang'd; ſome there are who hang down their heads, and grief pinches them, others fume and fret, and are very wrath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: But theſe carry their <hi>Muks</hi> in their <hi>Foreheads,</hi> and any Man may know them. And it is certain, whoever wiſhes the Deſign had ſucceeded, or is ſorry and uneaſie that it did not, is guilty of the <hi>Perjury</hi> and <hi>Murder,</hi> if not of the <hi>fore-laid Contrivance:</hi> But which I chiefly aim at, is the <hi>exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſturbance,</hi> that the Miſcarriage of this Deſign, creates to ſome ſort of Perſons, which plainly indicates, that they themſelves are in the bottom, they find their Meaſures broken, their plots defeated, and turn'd upon them; and this is that which ſtrikes to the quick, and grates their Heart ſtrings. By their <hi>Pulſes</hi> you may diſcern the Motion of their <hi>Hearts.</hi> Would not you think it a very harmleſs, at leaſt, if not a very pious thing, for Men to rejoyce, when they ſee innocent Men eſcape a Bloody Contrivance layd for their Lives? And yet at <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> when the Country gave Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of their Joy, for the Acquittal of theſe Gentlemen, with what Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and Confuſion did it ſtrike the Proſecutors? whereas every Man is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually concern'd, and ought to be equally pleas'd for the clearing of wrong'd Innocence. In like manner, at <hi>Cheſter,</hi> when the Priſoners were brought to the Bar, the Geutlemen of the Country in great Numbers accompanyed them, to teſtifie their reſpects to them, and the rather, by reaſon of the great Injury had been done them, Mr. Juſtice <hi>Eyres</hi> was exceedingly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleas'd
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51853:8"/>at it, and in great paſſion ſaid, <hi>He did not know who were the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soners from the other.</hi> And when the Gentlemen were diſcharged by Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, there was a great ſhout among all ſorts of Perſons, <hi>Ladies, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen,</hi> the <hi>Clergy</hi> and <hi>Commonalty:</hi> This, it ſeems, was a mighty Provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to Mr. <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and he could no longer bear it, but told them, That <hi>this ſhould be neither for the Advantage of the Gentlemen, nor thoſe that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended them;</hi> and in particular ſaid to the <hi>Clergy, that they deſerv'd to have their Gowns pull'd over their ears.</hi> Bleſs us! What is the Matter? Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Men rejoyce to ſee innocent Men pull'd out of the <hi>Paws of Harpies,</hi> but they muſt be menaced with Vengeance, and have their <hi>Gowns pull'd over their ears?</hi> It is well for the Gentlemen that they had no <hi>Gowns,</hi> or elſe they might have been threatned to have been <hi>pull'd</hi> alſo; but though they had no <hi>Gowns,</hi> there was ſomething elſe they had to be <hi>ſtrip'd of;</hi> and this is the next Conſideration.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A Reform of the <hi>Juſtices of Peace</hi> and of the <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>litia</hi> in theſe 2 Countries is now on foot, and under Conſideration, and moſt, if not all the <hi>Juſtices,</hi> and <hi>Deputy-Lieutenants,</hi> are to be turned out; it ſeems theſe Gentlemen had no more wit, but they muſt diſcountenance <hi>Perjury,</hi> and rejoyce at the happy delivery of their Friends, Neighbours and Relations, and now they muſt pay for it; for it plain they are <hi>diſaffected.</hi> By whoſe power and influence theſe things are done, I ſhall leave to the Wiſdom and Inquiry of the Parliament only I humbly crave leave to add this one Remark, That from hence it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears that ſome Perſons are paſſionately diſturb'd at the Miſcarriage of theſe <hi>Goodly Evidences,</hi> that for the <hi>Diſappointment,</hi> they are reſolv'd to be <hi>Revenged</hi> on the <hi>Two whole Counties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, <hi>Sir,</hi> let us put all theſe together, and Conſider, if you pleaſe, the <hi>Incapacity</hi> of theſe mean Fellons to make, or manage this Plot, the <hi>Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveableneſs</hi> of mens Perjuring themſelves, and Murdering Men, <hi>for the ſake</hi> of theſe Villanies. The <hi>maintaining</hi> theſe VVretches at a moſt Profuſe and Extravagant Rate, the <hi>Notoriety</hi> of their former Villanies; the <hi>Illegal Courſes</hi> to clap up the VVitneſſes which ſhould confront them; the <hi>mighty and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious Promiſes</hi> to encourage them to go through with if, <hi>the Signing of War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants</hi> for haſty Hanging them before they were convicted, or tryed; the <hi>Blank Warrants</hi> for taking up a great Number more, ſo ſoon as they had been Executed; the <hi>Mighty Paſſion and Diſturbance</hi> for the Diſappointment; <hi>the turning out of the Officers of Juſtice, and the Militia</hi> in both the Counties; the Plain Effect of a very <hi>keen Reſentment,</hi> I ſay put all theſe together, and then anſwer your ſelf, whether theſe four Raſcals are the Only or the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Contrivers of this Curſed Deſign; or whether they were only <hi>Tools</hi> and <hi>Inſtruments</hi> to put in Execution what others had contriv'd for them, and put them to act.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:51853:9"/>
            <p> Thus, Sir, you have the Caſe plainly before you, there is only one part yet remaining, and that is, <hi>The effectual Proviſion for the ſecurity of iunocent Men hereafter:</hi> This I ſhall ſay little to, becauſe the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament will ſoon contrive it, when they take it in hand, and eſpouſe it heartily, <hi>A ſtrict Inquiry into this Plot, and Exemplary Puniſhment of all who are found Guilty,</hi> is one good Means; and a <hi>Bill for Regulating Tryals in Caſes of High Treaſon,</hi> is another, wherein it may be provided, That the Priſoner ſhall have <hi>Cou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l, a Copy of the Indictment,</hi> and of the <hi>Jury, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Tim,</hi> for his Defence, and the Summoning his Witneſſes; and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it may, be made highly Penal, to Obſtruct, or Impriſon any of the Priſoners Witneſſes; That in it likewiſe ſome Care may be taken of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting this <hi>Profuſe Liberality</hi> to indigent Men, which is a Temptation to the Poor, and a Bait for Rogues: But I ſhall not ſuperſede the Debates in <hi>PARLIAMENT,</hi> nor preſcribe to their Wiſdoms; but I hope I may preſume to leave with them this ſingle Conſideration, That theſe Practices, are not only, to the great Diſhonour of GOD, the Scandal of Chriſtian, Religion, the Ruine of the Nation, and all the Civil Liberties, but that they themſelves (not as Truſtees and Repreſentatives, but) in their proper Perſons, are more immediately concern'd to guard, and find out ſome Defence againſt them; and they cannot but ſee themſelves directly liable, as their Perſons and Fortunes are higher and greater; Eſtates are Criminals more than Men. And though <hi>Young</hi> and <hi>Blackett</hi> are gone, though <hi>Lunt, Womble,</hi> &amp;c. are defeated, yet there are <hi>Rogues</hi> enough in <hi>England</hi> to be had for Money.</p>
            <closer>I am, <salute>SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Humble Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>There will ſhortly be Publiſhed a Perfect and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Narrative of the whole Proceedings, both at <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter</hi> and <hi>Cheſter.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
